this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer org
slash software hello this is Tobias for
software engineering radio today we are
starting a new chapter of our podcast
that is dealing with social aspects of
working as a software engineer and we
want to start by talking about company
culture and hiring in the software
industry I am very glad to have Randy
shop to talk with me on that topic Randy
has worked for various big companies
like Oracle eBay and even Google and
today he is the CTO at Kixeye hello
Randy welcome back to software
engineering radio Thank You Tobias it's
great to be back in episode 109 you
talked about architecture eBay and now
you are in the gaming industry how come
oh that's a fun transition so I worked
at eBay as the chief engineer for about
six and a half years and I talked a
little bit about those experiences and
things that I learned there in episode
109 like you say then I had my own
little startup after that and I like to
say I don't have my own Island so we
know how that went but it was very fun
and I learned I learned quite a lot I
worked at Google then as the director of
engineering for Google App Engine so
that's a platform as a service and about
three million different applications run
on the platform and then for the last
year or so I've worked as the CTO of a
gaming company called Kixeye in San
Francisco and the transition is an
interesting one I was very happy at
Google and eBay I learned a lot about
building very large systems and scaling
organizations from small to large and
one of the things that Kixeye is in the
process of doing is growing from small
to large so they were interested in
somebody who had experienced both
scaling infrastructures to support tens
of millions hundreds
millions of users and then also people
who know how to scale organizations to
support that that large amount and what
I found that I've I'm enjoying my time
at kicks I immensely the gaming industry
is extremely vibrant extremely fun
extremely passionate and what I'm able
to bring is like I say that sort of
large-scale Internet infrastructure eBay
and Google approach to server-side work
which is sort of where I have where I've
done most of my work but what I'm
getting to learn is the other half of
gaming which is the very exciting
graphics gameplay physics engine
simulation areas of computer science I
haven't touched in 25 years so it's it's
a lot of fun for me
Wow great but it has still been a big
step I supposed yeah so it again like I
say it's it's an opportunity for me to
help to bring some of these large-scale
server-side techniques that we that we
learn the hard way at eBay and Google
and apply them in an entirely new domain
and Kixeye makes I didn't say this but
Kixeye makes real-time strategy games in
both web browsers and and mobile devices
and the interesting part about that for
the engineering is the real-time so all
the things that one would learn about
building large-scale systems that have
extremely low latency and are very
highly responsive for users you know are
applicable whether you're doing it as a
platform and is in the case of Google
App Engine or as an e-commerce site as
an eBay or as a game as in Kixeye so a
lot of the lessons really all the
lessons are directly applicable so
that's that's been great for me our
today's topic is common to almost every
one of our listeners including me of
course but you're doing actually talks
on that topic why did you decide to go
out and share your opinion on hiring and
and culture and things around it oh
thank you for that's a great question I
think like you say because it's
universal I enjoyed I talked about lots
of different things you know I've talked
about
internet architectures you know
large-scale architectures for a long
time and I've been talking about
analytics and about DevOps but yeah the
like you say the culture and the hiring
and the people's side of engineering I
think gets a little bit we would say
short shrift you know it gets a little
bit under talked about and it's it's
extremely important for every company
you know whether we're whether you're
engineering or not but particularly in
engineering you know we think so much
about them about how to keep the
machines happy that we maybe don't spend
as much time as we should on keeping the
people happy yes
you all right do you remember your first
chance of actually influencing the
culture and a hiring process of a
company yeah well I suppose the obvious
well I mean I think every time anybody
is in any awkward any position where
you're responsible to hire somebody you
have at least a small impact right so I
mean even way back in the beginning of
my career almost 25 years ago at Oracle
you know we were hiring people and we
were trying to choose people that were
good team fit good cultural fit good
skills fit for the team but broadly in a
company I mean obviously the startup
that I worked on with you know after
eBay there were just two of us and so
every hiring decision was very much
forming a culture but the one that's had
the LAT the most I think lasting impact
is here at kick side so Kixeye is about
550 people based in San Francisco like I
mentioned and that's large enough to you
for us to be hiring for many different
positions all at once and also small
enough so that the culture hasn't maybe
congealed or you know is still malleable
is still able to be influenced and so
there was always already a culture of
course there before I joined but one of
the things that I've been trying to do
as a bit of a side project is to help to
bring some of the good things that I
took out of my experiences that eBay and
Google and then not to do some of the
less good things you know
and apply those so those are some of the
things that I've been talking about
recently yes is there a certain
situation that you can remember where
you wanted to change the way your
company is hiring and you were not
really in line with the culture of the
company but you were too early in your
career to actually change the
circumstances is this example something
you're now referring to as okay I want
to do it better now then let's say 20
years ago oh absolutely yeah I think I
mean I think in all situations whether
it's hiring or engineering practices or
whatever you know a lot of us and most
of us in the industry love what we do
and are passionate about it and want to
do the best and often have opinions
often strong opinions about how the
organization that we work in could do
things better so I can't in many ways I
can't remember a company where I didn't
feel like we could improve do you know
what I mean there there's an always an
opportunity to do things better and I
think you're absolutely I mean the
implication and the question I think is
absolutely right that you know you need
to have some it's helpful to have some
I'll say organizational leverage right
some influence over the organization to
help with that but you know anytime
you're in a position that no matter what
level you are anytime you're in a
position where you are actually
interviewing another person and I hope
that's true of basically every listener
who's an engineer that they're
interviewing people you know that's your
opportunity to influence and you know as
maybe you do more management and you
know that you'll have a broader
influence but but the influence that you
have you know just simply being in an
interview with another potential
candidate for your company you're both
obviously selling if you like I mean
that sounds a little crass but you're
both projecting to the candidate what
it's like to work in your group and in
your company and at the same time
evaluating that candidate against like
you know skill is fit for skills and
team and company culture so that's a
very direct and
personal way that everybody can have an
influence I think yes definitely
although I think this might vary
depending on which company you are
actually working with or which culture
you are living in because I think there
are main differences between the states
and working in the States and working in
let's say Europe or even Germany but we
will get back to this later do you think
that software companies actually focus
on different aspects or goals or tasks
then let's say manufacturing companies
or even plumbers oh do you think that
hiring is in the end everywhere
following the same rules
oh well that's an excellent question and
I'll say my sample size so my experience
is in mostly software companies and some
hardware companies where I work in the
software part you know Intel come you
know as an example but mostly I work in
the software industry but I would assume
it's here to your point that well I
guess the way I would answer is I think
there are many things that are common
and I think there are many things that
are different by industry right so the
things that are common you're looking
for are motivation and initiative you're
looking for cultural fit you're looking
for people that are good in the skit you
know can demonstrate effectively the
skills that they have and also that they
can communicate and collaborate with
other members of the team and I think
those are pretty universal I don't know
I mean you gave the example of a plumber
I mean most plumbers work individually
you know so there but but in a car
manufacturer or boy know that that needs
to be extremely highly organized you
know not just a few tens of people to
produce you know a piece of software but
thousands ten thousands of thousands of
people that are all all working together
to produce an automobile anyways so I
think that those soft skills if you like
you know are universal across most
across the different industries but yeah
in the software
we do have some challenges in that or
some differences in that what's the way
to say it we have some opportunity to
evaluate people's skills in an objective
way and I think you and I will talk
about that later in the interview but
for the most part software is a
sufficiently young engineering
discipline and some people would argue
it's not even yet an engineering
discipline to the level of that
mechanical engineering or automotive
engineering or aeronautical engineering
would be and so there we don't have for
example well-known and well-respected
sort of certifications that go a court
you know the concept in many countries
Germany and the u.s. in particular you
know a concept of getting a
certification as an engineer that
demonstrates you've done an
apprenticeship and multiple years of
training and so on there's not that
concept yet in the software and so in
some sense for the interview process we
have less to rely on outside of the
interview process and more to do within
the interview process if that makes any
sense you know because we can't you
can't implicitly people have in you know
lots of people have university degrees
that are relevant and you know work
experience and so on and you know those
are obviously good mechanisms to help to
evaluate people skills but but there's
not a common objective well respected
broadly you know covering concept of you
know engineer or something like that
right yeah not really standardized
definition of what and software engineer
actually is yeah something all the
companies are lacking of and have
problems with evaluating of course and
one thing I recognize is that you don't
really get manufacturers or let's stick
with my example plumbers through social
media and through other means I think
today companies are hiring software
engineers how do you and how does your
company find candidates yes that's an
excellent question and it's something
we're asking ourselves all the time
because kicks eyes based in San
Francisco and the San Francisco Bay Area
is particularly
in 2014 a very hot market by which it by
which I mean it's extremely challenging
to find well skilled engineers because
there are lots of companies that are
looking for many of the same people
there's a little bit of an edge to work
at a company where you make games but so
that fit that networks a bit in our
favor but but still you know there's a
lot of there's a lot of competition
which is a good thing yeah so how do we
find candidates I mean first and
foremost the best way to do it is direct
referrals from people that you you know
that I'll say for myself direct
referrals from people that work at
Kixeye who have worked with other people
you know and that's by far the best way
on a lot of different dimensions so it's
best in the sense that you know we the
person the Kixeye employee who knows
that the candidate has a very deep
knowledge about that person's skills
communication style cultural fit and so
on right if you've worked with somebody
for years that's a lot deeper knowledge
about them then a couple of one-hour
interviews right yeah so that's the
first and foremost the best way to do it
and that's true of every company of
every company LinkedIn has been godsend
to all this stuff both as a candidate
you know are potential candidate and as
a you know a company looking for
candidates I mean it wasn't too long ago
I mean before LinkedIn there was
basically no way you could find out
people's resumes yeah right you couldn't
find out their work experience without
asking them and so the ability just
simply I mean there's way more to it
than this but just simply the ability to
I'm gonna meet with somebody and I can
look them up on LinkedIn and typically
they've given some part of their
background and some context you know
that's hugely valuable and then being
able of course to search for people that
match particular skill sets who have
worked at other particular companies
that's usually valuable as well and then
of course there are a bunch of
aspects of the LinkedIn offering that
are specifically for recruiting and
those are even more you know even deeper
and more valuable but that but LinkedIn
has been a huge boon to both candidates
and and companies right because on the
flip side you know if you're looking for
a job here even if you're not you know
it's it's well accepted let's say it
this way it used to be that if you sent
out your resume you were looking for a
job right then you know and so the
company idea of simply getting your
resume out there was an implicit
indicator that you were unhappy and you
were looking for a new position right
and that's no longer true in LinkedIn I
mean it's just expected like I find it
odd when I you know they're handful of
people that I've met really just a
handful a handful of people I've met
recently personally or professionally
that don't have a LinkedIn profile and
they're typically in industries that
aren't software right this you know just
because it hasn't penetrated those
industries but but the vast vast
majority you know the 99 percent case of
people that I know personally or
professionally have some you know
reasonably detailed profile and LinkedIn
and that's hugely that's usually helpful
oh I guess the point that I was trying
to make was so now just simply having a
LinkedIn profile is no it doesn't
indicate anything about whether I'm
seeking a position or not does that make
sense
so it used to be that putting your
resume out was itself a an affirmative
indicator that I want to I want to work
somewhere else and now just simply
having a LinkedIn profile as expected
like that's a baseline expectation and
that's nice because it makes this is
real I mean hiring people is it's a
marketplace right I mean whether we
actually exchange money or not where the
general idea is that you are bringing
together producers of you know work and
consumers of work if you see what I mean
right
it's a bringing together of candidates
and companies is is what this is all
about and LinkedIn makes that very
seamless I mean it you know the analogy
is pretty obvious - its kind of the eBay
of of human talent yeah which is
interesting cause in Germany it's
actually not that important at all we
have but we have a different product
crossing which is taking the place
yeah sure there's nothing magic like you
I mean to your point there's nothing
magic particularly about LinkedIn it is
buffing in the US for sure but yeah I
mean it makes total sense that in
different markets there would be
different offerings and everything just
aids to build your own brand exactly one
of my one of my good friends and mentors
from many years back a guy named Gary
sponza who ran engineering at
informatica for many many years and for
whom I worked at Oracle in the early
part of my career said many years ago
and it was so pressing it he said you
know Randy you need to think about
building your own personal brand and the
wording was exactly that and I thought
well brand that sounds like marketing
and I'm an engineer and I don't do that
but then I've been I mean I've thought
about that in the years since and he was
absolutely right you know so yeah for
that I encourage obviously you know the
baseline thing is to have the LinkedIn
profile or the the German equivalent of
course right and that and equivalently
there's a Chinese equivalent you know
LinkedIn isn't big and China you know
that's our thing right you know in
Japanese I'm sure you so different you
know do the moral equivalent of of that
in your market so that's the baseline
but then sharing you're sharing your
skills and code by a github speaking at
first attending conferences and meetups
well meetups I guess you know to start
with that because they're relatively
inexpensive and often local to where you
are and then attending and speaking of
conferences all these things are ways of
both giving to the community right
participating in the community and at
the same time you know crassly building
your own personal brand and that's
exactly how
the best way really I will say looking
back through my my personal career I
have all this is maybe odd but I don't
think so
every time I've made a job change it's
been not because of it's been because of
a personal connection right it's always
been a referral a friend of a friend and
many times it has been not because I was
affirmatively seeking it but because the
friend of mine or the friend of the
friend was looking for somebody with a
particular skillset and the more that
you can have that personal brand and
that personal set of connections and
that personal network you know the the
broader opportunities that you have to
find something that you really really
like to do yeah you know but then well
you were talking about the the referral
system in inverted commas and Linkedin
and stuff so you know so much about the
person once you actually get to talk to
it to him or her in the end what is the
the actual purpose of an interview then
if you know so many things about him or
her before that oh that's great so
ideally what you would find out through
LinkedIn and github and various other
mechanisms is that the skills of the
person right but what you don't know is
anything about how they would fit in
your team or in your company culture so
I guess these are all equally important
we interviews are the in you cannot find
out cultural fit in an easy way from you
know LinkedIn so there you need personal
connection and whether that's
interviewing somebody remotely over
Skype which is actually we do a lot in
this and works well and in person
obviously you know as well so you're
sober doing all the kind of human the
evaluation of the human how is this
person how would this person potentially
fit in to the team and into the company
and then the other thing is you know the
evaluation of somebody's coding skills
and thing
skills is a lot easier to do when you
can have a back and forth right you and
I are having a conversation now and it's
a lot more it's a lot deeper because we
can go back and forth and whether we
were talking with that would be true
whether we were talking about code or
about hiring you know so that's the
other that's the other part of it and we
do this a Kixeye and other places do as
well for particular skill sets we have a
sort of coding test you know that we
give to people that they can do sort of
a take-home thing and they work on it
you know please build us well we don't
do this but you know build me a
real-time strategy game and you know
show it to me but you know one could
imagine doing something that gives
people an opportunity to demonstrate
their skills and then you can talk
through that in the interview you know
well why did you make this design choice
let's talk about it and that's a hugely
hugely valuable because at the end of
the day you know this is true as much at
Kixeye as it ever was at eBay and Google
we're looking for smart motivated people
and you know it's nice it's a nice to
have when somebody comes in with a skill
set that we already that we want you
know but it's it's almost obviously
almost more important it is exactly more
important that they be that they have
the ability to learn that same right
because one of the one of the things
that I think doesn't work well in hiring
at least in the software industry is
trying to have a particular like I'd
rather hire a person that can learn the
skill whether that you know Scala and
NACA or you know a game game AI engineer
or graphics like I'd rather hire
somebody I mean ideally of course
somebody has already been doing it for a
long time
but as between somebody who has that
particular skill but know others and is
limited whether because of interest or
because of skills to just that one thing
you know I'd rather hire somebody who
can who's a broader more we say full
stack engineer right somebody who can go
up and down and left and right in the
stem
then somebody who's very specific to one
particular technology right and I'm I
don't I don't want to leave people the
impression that we're only looking for
kind of undifferentiated cogs and
everybody's all the same like no I mean
I'm I would be a terrible graphics
program or a terrible UI programmer so I
don't at all claim that people don't
have expertise or interest but what I am
looking what we are looking for people
that are broad in those interests and
skills rather than extremely narrow yeah
and it kind of limits the ability of
your company to develop in a different
region or in a different way once you
decide okay let's do this and that stack
or this in that language since it's
coming up and every everyone is actually
following it if you have people who are
only limited to their skill set they're
good in it but yeah absolutely yeah
absolutely I agree I mean and and
actually one of the ways to indicate one
of the ways that people implicitly
indicate that is if they define
themselves as I'm an Oracle DBA I'm a
I'm a C++ engineer I'm you know and
there's really nothing wrong with being
expert in both in those areas right but
there's an interesting subtle thing
about whether you define yourself by the
particular stack and by the particular
skill or whether that's just something
you have expertise in but you're also
interested in learning other things you
know sure yes of course in some of your
talks that I've seen on the Internet you
were speaking about the concept of
hiring so-called a players and about the
strategy google has in terms of hiring
especially in terms of hiring people who
are who have a more open mind and not
just you know closely to this one skill
set or whatever what does that actually
mean to hire a players and and how would
you hire people in general great yeah so
let me just say what what I mean by
hiring a player so it is reasonably well
not reasonably
is very well documented and studied that
that particularly in creative industries
like software the difference in
productivity between the sort of most
productive people on the scale and the
least productive is not just like one
and a half or two times it's like ten
times so the most productive engineers
in a company sufficiently broad are sort
of 10x as productive as as the least
least ones so since that's true you're
bad you're better off as a company when
you have this opportunity to hire those
10x people because a you can hire fewer
of them and B if you hire fewer of them
you can have smaller teams and simply by
having a smaller team there will be a
lot less communication and coordination
overhead and the team can be more
productive so all else being equal a
company is much better off hiring
somebody that's more skilled rather than
less skilled and I don't actually say
experience because the well there's some
one hopes there's some relationship
between the amount of time that
somebody's been doing a particular skill
it's not linear or you know obvious that
you know just because somebody's been
doing it longer that they're necessarily
more productive okay so we'll just start
with that that's sort of how I define it
but you ask a very excellent and subtle
point about well is that an objective or
a bit subjective well think of it as
their world cup is going on right now
and so if you know the national team's
of the best national teams don't have
all the same player right you know we
have their people that they're a they
actually can play lots of different
things because they're skilled in all
the skills but they but form a team but
you know a great national team is formed
from a combination of players that have
different skills and different abilities
and a particular player that's excellent
on one team you know isn't necessarily
going to be a good fit for another right
the Brazilians play different a
different flavor of soccer than our
football excuse me
then the German team then the Spanish
team you know then the Dutch team etc
and so the best player for a particular
team fit is particularly a bit unique to
that team if that makes any sense
yes and sometimes the coach would even
be forced to swap players because the
second-best player is actually fitting
best in the team and is able to help the
team more than the individually better
player exactly yeah
so when you're evaluating I mean really
at the end of the day you the goal is to
make the team productive right so and so
to form you know we're using a bit the
football analogy and it's a good one
another analogy as a symphony you know
you want to have lots of different
players of instruments that are each
individually skilled in their own areas
but it may not be true that the
absolutely highest skilled cellist is
the best one to play in your quartet
right it is almost certainly true that a
fit to that quartet or to flip again a
rock band like this you know that's even
a better analogy because it's more sort
of visceral for most of us the best
guitarist is not the best fit for any
possible rock band you know what I mean
yes I do yeah so so yeah so anyway so
back to back to the question general is
you know you want to find the people
that are going to be most productive in
your area and you know there's a
baseline level of skill of course but
the cultural fit is just as important
okay so that means that if a company
says that they are hiring only a players
or the so-called top 10%
then this does not have to mean that a
second company is actually talking about
the same exactly the same people when
they want to hire a players so it
depends on whether they fit to the
culture and have the rights and needed
expertise and so it's not that we leave
90 percent of the real population behind
yeah I think that well I think part
partly that's absolutely true where one
hopes that the top 10% of people that we
would want to hire of the overall pool
the top 10% of those as defined by
Kixeye is somewhat non-overlapping with
the top 10% who would want to you know
the sa P would be working looking for or
you know Google or eBay I mean there is
some overlap there's actually quite a
bit of it and so the the way I would say
that back is we're looking for people
with the best skill sets we can who also
fit into our team culture okay right and
so you know I will I will say that well
let's say it this way that a C player to
look on the other and there's probably a
universal evaluation skills wise of the
C player and you know people can get
better of course yeah but but yeah the
the very very specific you know once
you've filtered out for being top top of
your game in the skills you know again
we're coming back to the football
analogy right I mean their goalie or or
the striker needs to have a certain not
even baseline a certain extreme level of
excellence to be able to play at at the
World Cup level and then from there it's
there's a bit of a team you know the
team fit is the extra added one on top
of that if that makes any sense yes it
does it does one one actually aspect you
you are pointing out in your talks which
I really like is then see flyers higher
C players or or maybe B players higher C
players more often than a players cause
there's this competition going on
and they don't really want to be
overruled by someone who is actually
more skilled which I really like and I
think maybe the the term to hire a
players is just to see in a perspective
of who is hiring whom and how this
affects the whole team and the team
effort does it make sense it makes a lot
of sense yeah and I'm glad you brought
up that because that's the other aspect
of a players is that you want them
obviously to be you know again you're
trying to maximize the productivity of
the team that you'd have but you also
want that team to be a sustainable kind
of organism right and the best way to
get an a player is to have a group of a
players already you know because first
of all that's and that's very attractive
for the candidate wow these guys are
really amazing I want to work I want to
work with them I affirmative ly want to
work with those people so that's the
first step the flip side of that is that
the a players that you have are not
afraid of bringing on in fact they're
welcome they want to work with the best
you know they're they're confident in
their own skills they want to work with
other excellent people and so they
affirm you know the people that are
currently in your team are affirmative
ly looking for people that are the best
because they can learn from them and and
so on a lot of being an a player frankly
is an attitude about learning yeah you
know about always growing that's how you
get there but yeah but sadly it's it's
true that so a players tend to hire
other a players but yeah like you like
you brought up B players tend to hire C
players and the intuition there is that
there's a whether conscious or
unconscious a sort of lack of confidence
or you know fear underlying fear about
being sort of overshadowed and so you'll
find people that you know sort of B
player level don't want to hire in a
player because gosh they're worried for
their own position or something like
that
and an even sadly somebody who's equal
is a potential threat yes and so that's
where you get the B play
haier see players and you do see that
sadly and a lot of you know I'll say you
know I know only in the US but you know
their traditional extremely large
organizations often have that problem
you know they'll end up higher in the
sort of level of hiring kind of tends to
degrade over time and and that's very
unmotivated for the few a players that
are left you know and they end up
leaving and it makes it really difficult
to kind of turn that thing around you
know and go back in the other direction
yes definitely when I watched your talks
on the Internet it seemed that you
admire the Google way of hiring can you
tell how it is different to the inverted
commas normal way and why you prefer it
over other methods absolutely yeah so
let me first say the goal and people can
of course Google for to learn about this
so I'm not saying anything that's you
know secret and internal to Google it's
sort of well well expressed publicly so
yeah just briefly though let's start
with Google's goal Google's goal is to
hire a players yeah you know referring
to that back to the earlier thread of
our conversation and Google's goal is to
hire only a player so imagine the hiring
process is a sort of pipeline and out
the other end they want only eight
players to be you know absorbed into
into Google so Google is willing Google
is willing to have they say false
negatives but never false positives and
I'll explain what I mean by that a false
negative is where they so I want to go
there let's say you know and they say
sorry Randy this Google's not a good fit
for you and they're okay with making a
mistake like oh actually Randy should
have come you know but we're okay with
making a mistake and letting him go
potentially but they are never they
would never want to have a false
positive which is they would hire Randy
but Randy acts
wasn't a good fit at Google so
everything is organized around
everything about the process is
organized around that goal and so to
start from the candidates perspective
there are the candidates go through a
very deep and detailed set of four
technical positions of technical
interviews and I'll just say for myself
that you know I studied for weeks with
an algorithms textbook before I before I
did my Google interviews and I've been
doing this for a long time so and that's
that was well worth it because the
technical interviews are very deep and
and very challenging that's good for two
reasons one its a good filtering
mechanism but it's also a good
demonstration or signaling of how
serious Google is about engineering so
giving a tough interview to a candidate
is a good thing from the perspective of
filtering to see where the candidates
sort of strengths and weaknesses are
that's one value but the other value
which I think people under appreciate is
that you're signalling to the candidate
hey we're serious about this position
right if you come here we're you know
we're gonna mix this is a great place to
work exactly because we're so we put so
much effort into the into the interview
and it's so difficult right you know
people like challenging thing that's
right that's why people like to play
games like the games that we make a kick
sign you know people love challenges
right so Google is not intending to make
it a game I'm not trying to trivialize
that but there are happen there are two
halves to this thing and I think the
second half isn't as appreciated okay
so interview process very difficult and
then multiple rounds of interviews
typically as a standard at lots of
companies but Google has learned over
time how to do this and is constantly
refining the process so one thing that's
different one of them several things
that's different about as you say normal
interviewing or you know at other places
is it's not the hiring manager for the
position who makes the choice about
whether you know let's say Randy would
come to Google and there's actually an
objective evaluation based on those
interviews so all the interview feedback
that the interviewers have taken goes to
a hiring committee which is not made up
of anybody who interviewed the candidate
or anybody any of the hiring managers
and that hiring committee sees there are
many hiring committees but let's imagine
that there were just one conceptually
they're seeing sort of all of the
candidate flow right and so they're in a
very good position and they're all
senior and for technical and senior
engineers at Google who've been around
for a long time and really know what it
means to work at Google what the Google
culture is like and so on and so they're
looking for all those in a sort of
somewhat objective way looking for
people that would be a good fit at
Google and they make the determination
about whether Randy should or should not
be given an offer then then totally
separate as a separate concept you know
once they've decided yes we'd like to
make an offer to Randy or Tobias then
there's a separate concept about okay
where should we place this person in
Google you see what I mean
and so then then interviews if you like
with with hiring managers and with
particular groups come after that
but those interviews tend to be less
about evaluating the candidates skills
and more about evaluating cultural fit
in the team you know so they tend to be
more though that final thing tends to be
more of a set of casual conversations
about team fit as distinct from the more
rigorous skills fit if you see what I
mean and I really like that
differentiation you know in some sense
it works well for Google because there's
a huge amount of candidate flow so the
fact that there's a lot of filtering
along the way is okay because there's
enough input into the pipe you know in
the beginning but the end result is that
you know a lot in my you know limited
experience you know the the people that
have come out the other end of that
funnel are extremely skilled extremely
motivated and really good cultural fit
so on average
you know there's a high I think this is
very anecdotal from my perspective but
that this process has a higher success
rate than other processes you know
because it's so because it's rigorous
and objective going along and it also
again like I say demonstrates the
seriousness to the candidate of you know
demonstrates this is a really really
great place to work
yes I'd like to discuss two aspects of
this way of hiring and I know it's not
only Google who is doing it this way but
other companies learn from them
the first one is that it seems like
sometimes or maybe more often Google is
only rejecting people because they were
applying for the first time and the
second one is it looks like the tests
are only focused around data structures
and algorithms isn't that a bit narrow
and do you think that other valuable
people are left behind and maybe even
the majority of the applicants are left
behind oh yeah those are great questions
yeah so the first one was about the
false negatives and so let me just let
me try to describe that again so again
the goal of the hiring process is to
make sure that only sort of a players
only good skills and cultural fit
candidates end up being offered a job
and it's not that the hiring process
there's nothing there's any advantage to
rejecting people
it's just that Google understands very
openly and explicitly we're gonna make
mistakes we we know we you know but this
is when I work there so we Google
understand that we will make mistakes in
this process and we will reject people
that we really should have hired and
that's totally known so that hiring
committee that I mentioned as part of
their sort of evaluation of the
candidate so they can say hire and then
they can say no hire but then when would
that person be asked to reapply right
and so
you know what this in so the
conversations that I overheard in a
bunch of these committees went something
like this you know she has it she you
know she she did okay in the interviews
she you know messed up a few things so
she's not a good she's not gonna be a
hire right now but you know what I think
you know she showed a lot of promise and
now she knows how the hiring process
goes so let's ask her to reapply in six
months and then and then hopefully
she'll she'll reapply and and go through
the second time but I just want to be
clear that it's it's about everybody rec
everybody that's part of the process
recognizing that the process is
imperfect and that it will reject people
that really should be there and so this
idea of a rejection from Google is not a
permanent you know never ever talk to
Google ever again and I hope candidates
who have been rejected don't feel that
way you know they should they should
they're actually encouraged to reapply
later on and if they you know still
really want to really want to work there
and then the second time they may go
through and that's actually extremely
climene there are people at Google
several of them you can google about
them you know written blogs about how to
get hired at Google
Stevie eggie is a good example he didn't
get in in the first time you know and he
writes about that very explicitly he
went through the first set of interviews
he was rejected he said wow this was
really hard and he did a bunch of
studying and so you can read his whole
blog it's really great I read it before
I interviewed you know read that whole
description of his experience he said
you know what I really want to work here
so he studied really hard and he
reapplied and and then he got in the
second time so again the rejection is
not something that the rejection isn't
motivating for people or the rejection
somehow a good thing it's just I just
want to be clear that it's the Google
process being open and recognized open
and honest with itself and recognizing
that it makes mistakes yes sorry the
second part of the question was up yes
does Google does the Google hiring
process select for some particular
subset of potential candidates and leave
off another set of people that really
should be there and the specific example
you gave and it's a good one is hey
you're you're basically
testing for people's knowledge of
algorithms and data structures from
their first couple of years of
university if you study if you studied
computer science and again I'll start
with the record the open recognition
that people understand in this process
that the process makes mistakes but
again coming back to the a player is
you're trying to find you know and again
will maybe use the football analogy
everybody's got to be able to dribble
the ball and pass accurately and so a
baseline knowledge of algorithms and
algorithms and data structures is
something that Google has said you know
look this is a baseline set of skills we
want everybody to have but the nice
thing frankly as a can if you're if
you're not if you don't feel if you feel
a little bit rusty in those areas you
know you can study that stuff and that's
encouraged it's not rocket science yeah
but it but it I mean I'll say for myself
you know I've been doing this for a long
time and when I applied I did study that
you know I got I got an algorithms
textbook that was recommended and I read
it cover to cover and I thought
carefully about it and I did a bunch of
you know programming exercises myself
and it really helped and obviously you
know the implicit part of the question
is somebody you know walking through the
halls of Google and constantly testing
you on you know what's the complexity of
this particular algorithm in this you
know what's the space complexity or time
complexity of X or Y or Z like no that's
not happening right you're not getting
you know shoved up against the wall and
when you're when you're walking around
as a Google employee but it's a baseline
set of skills that is at least
objectively able to be evaluated you
know what I mean I mean that's the other
aspect of it is that look you know Randi
either knows or doesn't know the
appropriate usage of a hash table or a
linked list or different flavors of
red-black trees or so on you know what I
mean like that that's an abbess
objective and I don't want to leave
people with the impression that that's
the only criterion that you're being
evaluated on but it's a baseline right
right just to make sure that we are not
only talking about Google I'd like to
ask you if you would want to apply those
describe
it's procedures to your hiring process
at Kixeye or if you would want to change
something or do something different
cause it fits better to kick side then
the inverted commas Google way of hiring
that's an excellent question sure so we
have not adopted wholesale the the
Google hiring process but we've started
in the last year to add more rigor to
the process so one way that we do that
is we've always had like I mentioned
sort of coding guests take home coding
tests for people in particular areas and
we've started to do more of those
because we found those to be hugely
valuable for the same reason right
because it's a it's a sort of a somewhat
objective way of giving people an
opportunity to demonstrate their skills
and at the same time it's a it's a deep
it's a good way of having of in some
sense having an icebreaker or starting a
conversation you know hey I noticed that
in your in your coding test you know you
approach it in this way and let's talk
about that and what were the trade-offs
that you thought you know what I mean
it's it's a way of starting those
engineering interviews farther ahead in
some sense in the conversation than you
otherwise would have been able to be
that does that make sense
definitely it does and if it is only for
this reason then it is really great yeah
and I guess the other aspect is being
more explicit in the downstream process
so we don't have a separate hiring
committee you know we're sort of not at
that at that size or shape yet but but
we do we have entered injected more sort
of rigor downstream in the process and
that's helpful okay what fraction of
your time
and or your team's time do you spend on
recruiting and hiring right now oh
that's a good one we have a number I
mean we're a 500-person company and we
have six full-time recruiters so I'll
tell you that it's a it's a very
important you know effort that we put
lots of effort on you know from the
whole company for me and my team
personally yeah we probably what we
order ten fifteen percent twenty
percent sometimes okay so a decent a
decent chunk of time and it ABS and
flows right but but we spend a lot of
time and effort evaluating candidates
and making sure they're good they're
good fits and then also each of us kind
of back to our earlier conversation
leveraging our own networks when we when
we when we're looking for somebody
leveraging our own networks to find to
find people because again like I said
before the very very best way I mean we
talked a lot about a detailed interview
process but the very best way to find if
somebody's a good fit is to know them
already right you know cuz there's no
there is just to be super honest and to
reiterate there's you know let me make a
little bit of a joke the standard hiring
process is a little bit like you talk to
somebody for an hour and then get
married by guess that's crazy
it is that's totally insane and so the
only way and this is well the a far
better way and a far more productive way
for everybody involved is to have known
somebody I like to take the analogy and
I way that isn't really very appropriate
somebody that you work with has already
dated them for multiple years no our
Dean already knows them really well and
knows that they're gonna be a bit you
know I guess that analogy doesn't work
well but the but but that but the fact
you know again we've had the best
success both in terms of interest in of
candidates coming to Kixeye and then
also for success for people once they're
here but best success from referrals of
people that have worked with you know
the candidate for a long time before and
there's no substitute for that right
there's nothing we can do in a handful
of hours no matter how many tests no
matter how objective we are no matter
how detailed or fast we talk you know
there's no way we can substitute for oh
yes I work with this person for three
years at this company and here's why
she's wonderful and here where her
skills here here where her strengths and
weaknesses and so on well it's a matter
of time in the end so and you don't have
it exactly exactly and yeah
I'd like to ask you a question which is
particularly important for me as a
German person and maybe for all our
listeners who are living in Asia and
Europe and not in the States do you
think that the described techniques are
in contrary to cultures in other nations
than the US for example if I as a German
person just because I applied for the
first time at your company I would have
a really hard time reapplying after six
months I think I wouldn't simply do it
do you think that this notion is wrong
and do you think that there are some
general aspects which can be applied on
every country when you want to hire a
person of that nation or do you think
that you have to adjust your techniques
for every person in every country that's
a great question and I'll just say to
start that my experience is limited to
hiring in America and particularly
hiring in Silicon Valley so I'm very
open to the idea that not all of these
practices are gonna translate even
across the United States let alone
across into Europe and Asia
so to your point I think I would be
surprised if there weren't differences
globally Yeah right I would be very
surprised no that said I think that I
also agree with the implicit part of the
last part of your question which is do I
think that there are some universals
absolutely I do
right and looking for I mean I'm sort of
looking for a team or cultural fit
looking for people that are motivated
and have good communication and good
collaboration my suspicion is that those
are universal qualities you know that
make people successful but the details
of how the process works I think I I
would be surprised if we would not want
to specialize if you like those those
processes in like you say in Germany or
in China or Japan or some other place
like it has to be true that they should
be different country by country but I'll
say you know I'll just be open that you
know my experience
is well is hiring I mean I've worked
I've worked at companies which were
global and helped to hire people
globally but but yeah idea I like I said
I'd be surprised if there weren't
individual cultural differences but I'd
also be surprised if the ideal process
for finding someone in Germany or in
China or Japan for example to join your
company would be entirely different from
an American journey mean like there's
clearly some overlap but there's clearly
not 100% overlap if that makes it exact
yes I'm with you in this case I'm
definitely one aspect of your talks that
I really do like is that you're talking
a lot about constant rethinking of your
strategies and you really promote this
idea is this applicable to hiring as
well or the way you are hiring
absolutely so I think I think we should
always as people and as organizations we
should always be thinking about how can
we do better
because we're all we're all on a journey
to improve ourselves whether the
ourselves are people or or organizations
or whatever and and to start with the
the baseline that you need for that is
to be open and honest with yourself
about what the trade-offs are you're
making you know what are my goals here
what and then what what are the
trade-offs and - yeah I mean so so I
think organizations should always be
looking to improve themselves and yeah
that's that's applicable to anything so
it's particularly for the hiring process
you know I've come back to the Google
analogy Google was does a great job of
collecting data about things you know
collecting data about the hiring process
that they've had for 15 years and
they've been constantly refining it and
so what I described was my experience as
I've sort of you know 2013 the hiring
process at Google but that evolved over
time and it's going to continue to
evolve and I think that should be true
at every at every company you know
companies changed their their goals you
know their overall
goals company-wide and then there are
specific goals for individual
organizations and then you'd want to be
changing your certainly the things
you're looking for when you're hiring
but also maybe the process itself of
hiring as you go along right I mean it's
I guess the way to say it is for me you
know it would be a bit silly to think
that the hiring process that we have
right at any company right now is the
perfect process forever yeah right
that's that sounds that sounds
reasonable and a good thing because I
think I think sometimes especially when
it comes down to hiring there's this
notion of okay we got it right now and
this is global and it's good to hear
that this shouldn't be the case just
maybe maybe if you know how do you
measure success in this case do you know
how Google is doing it or how are you
doing this
sure yeah I'll say how we do it which is
we measure so as with any company you
know we evaluate individual people
regularly you know that's just a normal
a normal process of giving people
feedback on how well they're doing and
how they can improve so that's a good
indicator of whether somebody is a good
fit you know that we just sort of are
evaluating people regularly and then so
that reflects on the hiring process
obviously then of course you know
retention of people people wanting to
that's a that's a good indicator as well
there's another indicator of success so
the hiring process is a funnel right so
and then so you can evaluate different
if you like stages of that funnel over
time and that's helpful to see if
improvements or changes that you've made
in the process are more or less
effective do you know what I mean
so what what sort of percentage of
people have passed particular phases of
the funnel and you know is more better
as less better but noticing those
changes are a good metric if you like
for how to evaluate it
yeah Google does a good job of Google
does the same thing so you know they do
as again any company they do evaluations
of individual people on a regular basis
individual employees so that's a good
indicator and then also retention and a
kind of funnel analysis of the of the
process right okay good
um I'm afraid we need to leave it with
that we actually plan to talk a lot more
about company culture and competition
and things like that and I hope that we
could set a dates where we can talk
about the second half of our schedule
absolutely sure no I'd love to do that
yeah just one general question you're
talking about hiring but actually are
doing something totally different right
now by the time we are speaking you are
in Germany what are you doing if you're
not talking about hiring when I'm not
when I'm not giving talks about hiring
yeah
well the joke is I'm actually hiring so
that's what one part of it is actually
doing the hiring process but you know
but but I'm the CTO of Kixeye and my
responsibility is to run the group so we
have many different games and my
responsibility is to run the all the
shared engineering that is used across
all the games and so that's my that my
day job is to is to run that
organization and that's sort of
technical leadership and also
organizational leadership so yeah so
I'll be traveling back in a few hours to
well actually over over an extended day
back to San Francisco and right and
early I'll be back in the office and
doing my doing my day job use you were
saying that you are hiring is kicks I
actually hiring right now do you want to
promote oh absolutely yes thank you sure
no kicks I is always hiring
and now as much as any time so we have
off so we have about 550 people
worldwide and
sort of 450 of those are in our main
office in San Francisco so we're hiring
there we also have offices we're hiring
in all these places we have offices in
Victoria British Columbia in Canada we
have an office in Brisbane Australia
where we build one of our games we have
an office in Portland where we do our
customer support and then we have a
small office in Seattle and a small
office in Amsterdam so in all those
places we're looking for talented people
and you know all up and down the stack
so we do real-time strategy games so
we're looking for people on the front
end to do user interface and graphics
and sort of the simulation the gameplay
side of things which is extremely
important and then we're looking for
very strong server-side engineers as
well to build the server side of our
games and then gosh people to do
analytics and people to build the
infrastructure for analytics quality and
automation people you know I strongly
suggest if anybody is it all interested
to go to WWE sicom slash jobs and you'll
see all the things that we're looking
for right now great and if someone wants
to actually meet you or see you talk at
a conference where will you be in the
future times
let's see later in the fall I'll be
speaking at the go to conferences in
Copenhagen and aqua or hosts in the
Netherlands I'm speaking at build stuff
which is in Lithuania in Vilnius in
November and there are still a few other
potential ones that were that we're
working through very impressive I can
only encourage you listeners to go to
the talks or watch the videos that we
have linked in the show notes I learned
a lot from them so Randy thank you very
much for being on the show
as we said there will be a second part
later this year but for now thank you
very much and have a good day bye great
Thank You Tobias this was a lot of fun
so this is the end of our episode with
Randy show
we want to encourage you to go to iTunes
and write a review of this show and if
you have something to add or some
comments then feel free to go to our
website se - radio dotnet and leave a
comment at this episode this is to be a
Scott's for software engineering radio
thank you for listening thanks for
listening to se radio an educational
program brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine for more information
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se - radio
net to support us you can advertise su
radio by clicking the Digg reddit
delicious or slide buttons on the site
or by talking about us on Facebook
Twitter or your own blog if you have
feedback specific to an episode please
use the commenting feature on the site
so that other listeners can respond to
your comments as well this and all of
the episodes of se radio is licensed
under the creative commons
two-point-five license please see the
website for details thanks again for
your support
[Music]
[Applause]